Cyril Clemens Papers
Cyril Clemens Papers
1927-1982
Clemens, Cyril, 1902-1999.
1.75 linear ft.
Correspondence, writings and memorabilia of the American author and Twain biographer.
2578779
Biographical History
Cyril Coniston Clemens was born in in St. Louis, Missouri, on July 14, 1902. After attending Canterbury School in New Milford, Connecticut, he continued his education at St. Louis University High School, attended Georgetown University, and received his B.A.. and M.A. degrees from Washington University (St. Louis). He married Nan B. Shallcross on October 8, 1933. He was a distant cousin of Samuel Langhorn Clemens and spent his life researching, writing about, and otherwise promoting his famous cousin. A family inheritance enabled him to devote time to these pursuits, including offering a life membership in the International Mark Twain Society, which he founded in 1930, to hundreds of important individuals. He also founded and edited the Mark Twain Quarterly, 1936-1982. His writing include biographies of Twain and Truman and short sketches of famous authors and politicians, including George Bernard Shaw, A.E. Housman, Mussolini, Sir Robert Walpole, and John Galsworthy. He died May 16, 1999.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Cyril Clemens Papers contain correspondence, writings, and memorabila.
Correspondence includes incoming and outgoing; correspondents include authors (Willa Cather, Will Cuppy, George Bernard Shaw), governors (J.P. Coleman of Mississippi, Orval E. Faubus of Arkansas, Luther H. Hodges of North Carolina, William G. Stratton of Illinois), congressmen (Harry Byrd, Thomas J. Dodd, Jacob Javits, John F. Kennedy, Herman Talmadge), and foreign dignitaries (David Ben Gurion, Francisco Franco, Feldmarschall Erich von Manstein, Austrian Chancellor Julius Raab, Prime Minister of Southern Rhodesia Sir Edgar Whitehead). An alphabetical list of correspondents (incoming only) may be found at the end of this finding aid.
Writings includes typescript manuscripts of articles, books, and essays, many on Mark Twain, as well as diaries and commonplace books covering more than ten years, printed material, and production records for three Twain projects.
Memorabilia contains miscellaneous materials about, Printed material, Scrapbook of newspaper reviews, and Miscellany (Box 4, 4 Folders)
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is divided into incoming and outgoing; incoming correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent (Box 1, Folders 1-4) while outgoing correspondence is arranged alphabetically by recipient (Box 1, Folder 5). Writings: Manuscripts are arranged alphabetically by title Writings: Diaries/Commonplace Books are arranged chronologically. Writings: Printed Materials and Writings: Production Records are arranged alphabetically by title.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- American Fiction; Literature -- American Poetry; Clemens, Cyril, 1902-1999.; Authors, American -- 19th century.; Authors, American -- 20th century.; Authors, British -- 20th century.; Biographers -- United States.; Biography -- 20th century.; Twain, Mark, 1835-1910 -- Family.; Articles.; Correspondence.; Diaries.; Essays.; Galley proofs.; Manuscripts (document genre); Scrapbooks.; Housman, Laurence, 1865-1959.; Cather, Willa, 1873-1947.; Authors.; Biographers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Incoming
    - A-C (Box 1)
    - D-H (Box 1)
    - J-P (Box 1)
    - R-Y (Box 1)
  - Outgoing
    - Bush, —; Porter, Katherine Anne; Williams, Florence (Box 1)
- Writings
  - Manuscripts
    - A-D (Box 1)
      "Albert Einstein and Some Letters," 6p. Typescript
      "An American Philosopher in Exile: George Santayana," 9p. Typescript
      "Chapter [?]: The Name and Nature of Poetry,"11p. Typescript
      "Chapter Nine: Housman and Fellow Authors," 12p. Typescript (incomplete)
      "Charles Waterton, Neglected Catholic," 8p. Typescript
      "A Chat with Sir Hugh Walpole," 9p. Typescript (carbon)
      "Colonel Charles Erskine Scott Wood," 6p. Typescript
      "Cordell Hull, Great Statesman," 7p.
      "Cyril Joad: Wisecracking Philosopher," 7p
      "David R. Atchison: President of the United States," 3p. Typescript
    - E-L (Box 1)
      "Fanny Hurst," 8p. Typescript
      "George Bernard Shaw," [6]p. Typescript and ms.
      "George Washington as a Sitter," 5p. Typescript
      "Granite or Putty: Coolidge's 'I do not choose to run.. .' ", 20p. Typescript. With Athern P. Daggett.
      "A Half Hour with Giovanni Papini," 9p. Typescript
      "History of American Literature" 73p. ms
      "Housman and Fellow Authors." 12p. Typescript (incomplete)
      "How Mussolini Made His First 'Y'," 5p. Typescript
      "Impressions of Sinclair Lewis with Some Letters," 5p. Typescript
      "Letters from Humorists Will Cuppy and Opie Read,' 12p. Typescript (carbon)
      "Lord Aston's American Visit: June-August, 1853," 7p. Typescript
    - M (Box 1)
      "Mark Twain and Bernard Shaw," 4p. Typescript (carbon)
      "Mark Twain and His Favorite Authors," 8p. Typescript
      Mark Twain for Young People, "Chapter Six," 6p. Typescript
      Mark Twain for Young People, "Chapter Seven," 6p. Typescript
      "Mark Twain's Private Audience with the Emperor of Austria," 2p. Typescript (carbon)
      "My Friend Ben Ames Williams," 6p. Typescript, with corrections by Mrs Williams.
      "My Visit to the Noted Novelist John Galsworthy at Hampstead," 8p. Typescript
      "My Visit with G.K. Chesterton," 10p. Typescript
      "My Visit with H.G. Wells," 8p. Typescript
    - N-S (Box 1)
      "Name and Nature of Poetry." 11p. Typescript
      "The New Shakespeare Discovery,"4p. Typescript
      "The Prince of French Biographers: Andre Maurois," 8p.
      Typescript Quotation from Twain's Mark Twain Wit and Wisdom. 1p. Typescript
      "Raphael Sabatini," 9p. Typescript, with emendations by Sabatini.
      "Senator's Job Was not for Mark Twain," 3p. Typescript (carbon)
      "Sir Anthony Hope Hawkins," 7p. Typescript
      "Some Sigrid Undset Letters," 8p. Typescript (carbon)
    - T-Z (Box 1)
      "Tea with John Drinkwater," 5p. Typesecript
      "Thomas James Wise; Master Literary Forger," 7p. Typescript
      "A Visit to Augustine Birrell," 9p. Tyepscript
      "A Visit to E.F. Benson at Rye," 8p. Typescript
      "A Visit to Sir Anthony Hope Hawkins," 7p. Typescript
      "Was Mark Twain a Dramatists?" 9p. Typescript
      "Young Mark Twain" pp.1-132, 142-144. Typescript
  - Diaries/commonplace books
    - 2 September 1925 to 2 June 1926, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 8 November 1927 to 19 August 1939?, 7 folders (Box 2)
    - 8 December 1952 – 28 August 1959, 5 July 1962, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Printed material
    - Articles from Hobbies magazine (Box 3)
    - Articles from newspapers and miscellaneous magazines (Box 3)
  - Production records
    - Mark Twain Jest Book, 32p., proofs? (Box 3)
    - Mark Twain, the Letter Writer, galley proofs (Box 3)
    - "Young Sam Clemens", partial proofs with corrections (Box 3)
- Memorabilia
  - Printed material
    - Mark Twain Journal, 1954; 1958 (Box 4)
    - Mark Twain Quarterly, 1949
    - Miscellaneous materials about, 1936-1979; undated (Box 4)
    - Scrapbook of newspaper reviews, 1933-1937 (Box 4)
  - Miscellany (Box 4)
- Alphabetical list of correspondents (incoming only)
  * preceding name = respondent is not addressee
  Anonymous. Note and poem about Twain’s trip to Australia.
  Anslinger, H.J.
  Armstrong, Terence Ian Fytton - see Gawsworth, John.
  Aronson, James
  Badt, Milton B. [3]
  *Balaguer, Joaquín [President, Dominican Republic]
  Barclay, Julius P. [Stanford University Libraries]
  Barr, Stringfellow
  Batson, Eric J.
  Beebe, Lucius
  Bell, Neil
  Bello, Francisco R. [Argentine Embassy minister]
  *Ben Gurion, David. [Office of the Prime Minister, Michael Nir, secretary]
  Benson, George S.
  Bishop, Jim
  Blomberg, Louise Martha von, Baroness
  Boyden, Frank L.
  Branch, E.M.
  Briggs, Frank J.
  Brown, Rollo Walter
  Brummall, H.H. [partial]
  Bullitt, William C.
  Bunche, J. Ralph
  Byrd, Harry Flood [Senator, VA]
  Castro, Adolphe de [2]
  Cather, Willa. 8 letters
  Chennault, Anna
  Chevillou, André
  *Chile. Office of the President.
  Christopher, George H.
  Clemens, Erwin
  Clemens, Henry
  Clemens, P.L.
  Coleman, J.P. [Governor of Mississippi]
  Cornish, Dudley T.
  Cramer, H. Leslie
  Cuppy, Will
  Curtis, Carl T. [Senator, NE]
  Dahl, Walter M
  *DeGaulle, Charles
  Delaplaine, Edward S.
  Dodd, Thomas J. [Senator, CT]
  Duke of Somerset
  Earl of Woolton
  Faubus, Orval E. [Governor, AK]
  *Franco, Generalísimo of Spain
  Fulbright, J.W. [Senator, AK]
  Garcia, Carlos [President of the Philippines]
  Gawsworth, John [pseud. of Terence Ian Fytton Armstrong]
  Gewelt, Oskar
  Gibbs, Philip
  Glenn, Frank
  Green, Howard [Sec. of State for External Affairs, Canada]
  Gregory, Ralph
  Hagedorn, Hermann
  Halleck, Charles A. [Rep., IN]
  Halliburton, Maurine
  Handley-Taylor, Geoffrey
  Harlan, John M. [Supreme Court Justice]
  Harnsberger, Caroline Thomas
  Hand, Norma [6]
  Hazen, David W.
  Hersey, John [copy]
  Hill, Mrs. Edith F. [Louisiana State University Library]
  Hodges, Luther H. [Governor, North Carolina]
  Housman, Laurence. 23 letters
  Hummel, Don [Mayor of Tucson]
  Huxley, Sir Julian
  Javits, Jacob K. [Senator, NY]
  Jenkins, Walter
  Johnson, Edgar
  Johnson, Lady Bird
  Johnson, Lyndon B. [Incl. photograph]
  Kennedy, John F. [While a senator from MA]
  Kerner, Otto [Governor, IL]
  Knapp, Paul C.
  Knecht, Karl Kae.
  Krauss, Bernard
  LaFarge, John
  Lewis, John L.
  *Lloyd, Selwyn [Chancellor of the Exchequer, UK]
  Mansfield, Mike [Senator, MT]
  Manstein, Erich von [Feldmarschall]
  Marshall, Bruce
  Martin Luther Universität, Halle
  Maugham, Robin
  McAnney, B.O.
  Melton, John L.
  Metalious, George
  Miller, J. Gordon
  Miller, Paul
  Moss, John E. [Rep., CA]
  Mottram, Ralph
  Murdock, Marcellus M.
  Newman, Robert P.
  O’Connor, Richard
  Paderevski, Serge
  Paul, W.S.
  Perrett, C.J.
  *Portugal. Presidencia do Conselho [2]
  Purdom, C.B.
  *Raab, Julius [Chancellor of Austria]
  Read, Opie - see Cuppy, Will
  Rogers, Will, Jr.
  Romulo, Carlos Peña
  Ross, Isabel.
  Royce, William Hobart
  Russell, Walter
  Sawyer, Grant [Governor, NV]
  Schaefer, Victor A. [University of Notre Dame]
  Schock, Mrs. William W.
  Schwengel, Fred [Rep., IA]
  Shaw, George Bernard
  Spaatz, Carl
  Sparkman, John [Senator, AK]
  Stratton, Leslie C.
  Stratton, William G. [Governor, IL]
  Strauss, Lewis L. [2]
  Strickler, Davis
  Stritar, Joze
  Talmadge, Herman E. [Senator, GA]
  Teele, Stanley F.
  Thomas, Lowell
  Trohan, Walter
  Uphaus, Willard
  Welch, Helen M. [University of Illinois]
  Wendt, Lloyd
  *Whitehead, Sir Edgar [Prime Minister of Southern Rhodesia]
  Williams, Ethel Carleton
  Young, Robert H.